<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
       '$RCSfile: eml-210info.xml,v $'
       Copyright: 1997-2002 Regents of the University of California,
                            University of New Mexico, and
                            Arizona State University
        Sponsors: National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis and
                  Partnership for Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans,
                     University of California Santa Barbara
                  Long-Term Ecological Research Network Office,
                     University of New Mexico
                  Center for Environmental Studies, Arizona State University
   Other funding: National Science Foundation (see README for details)
                  The David and Lucile Packard Foundation
     For Details: http://knb.ecoinformatics.org/

        '$Author$'
          '$Date$'
      '$Revision$'

    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
    it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
    the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU General Public License for more details.

    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
    Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
-->
<article class="faq">
  <title>Information for EML 2.1.1 Document Authors</title>
  <para/>
  <para>
    <ulink url="./index.html">EML Schema Documentation</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
    <ulink url="./eml-faq.html">EML FAQs</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>EML 2.1.1 introduces internationalization capabilities that can be used in most 
  text-based elements. Version 2.1.1 remains backward-compatible with the previous 2.1.0 release. 
  Authors can safely upgrade existing 2.1.0 documents to 2.1.1 without 
  altering any content, though adding additional language translations is encouraged.</para>
  <para>By allowing mixed element content, nested translation elements can be included without 
  altering or introducing ambiguity with respect to EML element cardinality. Translation elements 
  use standard xml:lang attributes to specify the language used for their content. Translation elements 
  can be nested such that child elements may inherit or override the language used by their ancestors.
  The top-level EML element may include an xml:lang attribute which will apply to every element in the
  document unless a child element includes a different xml:lang attribute to override the document default.</para>
  <para>Multi-lingual authors of EML should carefully consider their primary target audience when deciding 
  the default document language. Early adopters should be aware search tools like Metacat will require custom configuration 
  in order to search arbitrarily nested translations.
  </para>
  <para> </para>
  <!-- whats new in 2.1.1 -->
  <section>
    <title>Internationalization in EML 2.1.1</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry id="id.1">
        <question>
          <para>Including translations</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>The internationalization feature allows authors to place any language in
            &lt;value&gt; tags nested within most EML text fields. 
            The xml:lang attribute should be used to explicitly declare the language used.</para>
            
          <para>Additional documentation and examples are available in the EML specification. 
          The <ulink url="eml-resource.html#i18nNonEmptyStringType">i18nNonEmptyStringType</ulink> is used for simple text,
          while <ulink url="eml-text.html#i18nString">i18nString</ulink> for more structured text elements.   
            </para>
    </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </section>
</article>
