<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
       '$RCSfile: eml-210info.xml,v $'
       Copyright: 1997-2002 Regents of the University of California,
                            University of New Mexico, and
                            Arizona State University
        Sponsors: National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis and
                  Partnership for Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans,
                     University of California Santa Barbara
                  Long-Term Ecological Research Network Office,
                     University of New Mexico
                  Center for Environmental Studies, Arizona State University
   Other funding: National Science Foundation (see README for details)
                  The David and Lucile Packard Foundation
     For Details: http://knb.ecoinformatics.org/

        '$Author: obrien $'
          '$Date: 2009-02-22 23:58:01 $'
      '$Revision: 1.12 $'

    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
    it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
    the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU General Public License for more details.

    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
    Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
-->
<article class="faq">
  <title>Information for EML 2.1.0 Document Authors</title>
  <para/>
  <para>
    <ulink url="./index.html">EML Schema Documentation</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
    <ulink url="./eml-faq.html">EML FAQs</ulink>
  </para>
  <para> Several modifications to the EML schema made in version 2.1.0 will require changes to how 
  EML documents are structured, and these changes are highlighted here. EML authors should also 
  refer to the complete schema documentation for the affected sections for complete usage 
  information and examples. Existing EML 2.0-series documents can be converted to EML 2.1.0 
  using the XSL style sheet that accompanies this release, as described in section 2 below. </para>
  <para> The EML 2.1.0 release addresses several errors with respect to W3C specifications 
  for XML schema (http://www.w3.org/2001/03/webdata/xsv). Although the changes are small, 
  they are incompatible with EML 2.0.0 and 2.0.1 schemas, which necessitated advancing the 
  version number to "2.1". The STMML schema was also found to be invalid with respect to XML 
  Schema language, and the most reasonable fix for this bug also is incompatible with earlier 
  versions. EML users should note that the STMML schema error was <emphasis>not</emphasis> 
  related to elements used directly by EML (i.e., &lt;unitList&gt; or &lt;unitType&gt;). However, 
  EML imports all of STMML, and 
  authors of EML documents may have made use of other parts of the STMML schema. Therefore, 
  it was decided to advance the namespace used for STMML-related imports to "stmml-1.1", 
  in keeping with the EML version naming pattern. The STMML authors have been contacted, 
  and they are interested in our development and use of STMML. </para>
  <para> Other features and enhancements were added to this release that represent significant 
  improvements. The XML data type requirements for several elements were changed, in some 
  cases to constrain their content, and in other cases to increase flexibility. The names of two 
  elements were changed make them consistent throughout EML. In the literature schema two 
  elements were made optional so that EML could accommodate in-press publications where 
  the volume and page range are not yet known. Support for two new optional elements was 
  also added: a 'contact' tree can now be used in the literature module, and a ‘descriptive’ element 
  can be used in the distribution tree.</para>
  <para> For the most part, EML 2.1 does not include introduce major new features, or require a 
  shift in use or implementation. This There was a deliberate decision to balance the impact on 
  instance document authors with necessary schema maintenance, and to prepare the schema 
  for the next phase of planned improvements and features. Some of the changes to EML 2.1 
  are invisible to document authors; see the 'Readme' that accompanies the distribution for a 
  complete list of the bugs addressed, and for information of interest to developers.</para>
  
  <para> </para>
  <!--


whats new in 2.1 -->
  <section>
    <title>Changes and New Features in EML 2.1.0</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry id="id.1">
        <question>
          <para>EML Schema validity</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>EML allows authors to place any XML markup in
            &lt;additionalMetadata&gt; sections at the end of the document. The content
            model for &lt;additionalMetadata&gt; includes an optional &lt;describes&gt; 
            element so that references to EML nodes can be included as necessary.
            In EML 2.0 this element was placed alongside the additional XML content; 
            however, this construct is not allowed in XML Schema, and the error was 
            not reported by XML parsers available at the time EML 2.0 was released. 
            In EML 2.1.0, the error has been corrected by adding a child element
            to the &lt;additionalMetadata&gt; section to contain the
            "&lt;xs:any&gt;" XML content. Documents written against 2.1.0 will
            differ from 2.0.1 documents as follows:</para>
            
          <para>&lt;additionalMetadata&gt; sections now must include the child
            &lt;metadata&gt; to contain the additional XML markup. The optional
            &lt;describes&gt; element may still be included to reference a particular node
            of the document. Multiple &lt;describes&gt; elements can be included if needed. </para>
          <para> In EML 2.0.1, an additionalMetadata section looked like this: <programlisting><![CDATA[...
 <additionalMetadata>
 <describes>123</describes>
  <unitList>
   <unit name="speciesPerSquareMeter" 
         unitType="arealDensity" 
	 id="speciesPerSquareMeter" 
	 parentSI="numberPerSquareMeter" 
	 multiplierToSI="1"/>
  </unitList>
 </additionalMetadata>...]]></programlisting>
          </para>
          <para> In EML 2.1.0, the markup must be enclosed within &lt;metadata&gt; tags: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
<additionalMetadata>
<describes>123</describes>
 <metadata>
  <unitList>
   <unit name="speciesPerSquareMeter" 
         unitType="arealDensity" 
         id="speciesPerSquareMeter" 
         parentSI="numberPerSquareMeter" 
         multiplierToSI="1"/>
  </unitList>
 </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
...
        ]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.2">
        <question>
          <para>STMML Schema validity</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>EML makes use of the Scientific Technical and Medical Markup Language schema
            (STMML, stmml.xsd) for describing units, and the STMML schema was also found to 
            be invalid. The error was not related to
            elements used directly by EML (i.e., &lt;unitList&gt; or
            &lt;unitType&gt;), however some authors may have used other parts of stmml.xsd
            in their documents. The required schema changes were not compatible with STMML-1.0, and
            the EML development group is working with the STMML developers on this
            issue. Since EML now imports a version of STMML that is not identical to that available
            from its authors, it was decided to advance the namespace the EML 2.1.0 uses for stmml-related 
            files to "stmml-1.1". To import stmml.xsd into one of your EML 2.1.0 documents use the XML 
            namespace            declaration for STMML in the code below: <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<eml:eml
 packageId="eml.1.1" system="knb"
 xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1"
 xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd">
 <dataset>
	...
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
   <stmml:unitList xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 stmml.xsd">
    <stmml:unit name="gramsPerSquareMeter" 
                unitType="arealMassDensity" 
                id="gramsPerSquareMeter" 
                parentSI="kilogramsPerSquareMeter" 
                multiplierToSI=".001">			
     ..
   </stmml:unitList>
  </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>
		]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.3">
        <question>
          <para>Location of Access Control Trees</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1 an access tree could be included in each top-level module (i.e. dataset, 
          citation, software, or protocol) to control access to the metadata document. Additionally, 
          some authors put access trees in &lt;additionalMetadata&gt; sections and used
          &lt;describes&gt; elements to reference different nodes in the EML document to 
          control access to individual entities. Authors may have assumed that access 
          rules could be applied to any node with this practice. However, node-level access 
          control is problematic to implement, and in practice only access trees that reference 
          distribution nodes are recognized (as was stated in EML 2.0.1 documentation). 
          A better solution is to locate &lt;access&gt; nodes above or near the node to 
          which the access control should be applied, and this feature has been added to 
          EML 2.1.0. </para>
            
          <para> In EML 2.1.0, access trees can be placed in 2 locations. To control the entire
            metadata document (i.e., "document-level access"), an &lt;access&gt; tree should
            be placed as a child of the root element (<ulink url="eml.png">EML image</ulink>). If a
            metadata author wishes to override the document-level control for a specific entity, an
            additional access tree may be placed as the last child of a &lt;distribution&gt;
            element within the &lt;physical&gt; tree of that entity(<ulink url="eml-physicalDistribution.png">Physical Distribution Type image</ulink>).</para>
          <para>Example 1. To control access to all the metadata and by default to the data, use an
            &lt;access&gt; element at the top level: <programlisting><![CDATA[
<eml:eml>
 <access>
  ...
 </access>
 <dataset>
   ...
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata>
   ...
 </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>  
      	]]></programlisting>
          </para>
          <para>Example 2. Access rules can still be specified for any data entity by placing an
            access tree under that entity's physical/distribution element. The following example
            illustrates how a dataTable's access tree  can be used to override permissions 
            set at the document level.
            If no access is specified in distribution then the document-level access rules are
            applied. </para>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
<eml:eml>
 <dataset>
  ...
 <dataTable>
   ...
  <physical>
    ...
   <distribution>
    ...
    <access>
     ...
    </access>
   </distribution>
  </physical>
   ...
  </dataTable>
 </dataset>
</eml:eml>
       ]]></programlisting>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.4">
        <question>
          <para>Typing of &lt;gRing&gt; corrected</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>The content of the  &lt;gRing&gt; elementwas retyped to make these nodes more usable. This
            element is generally analogous to the FGDC component for ring. This element should now contain 
            a string       comprised of a comma-delimited sequence of longltude and latitude values for vertex
            coordinates (in decimal degrees), as in: <programlisting><![CDATA[
..
 <gRing>-119.453,35.0 -125,37.5555 -122,40 -119.453,35.0 </gRing>
..
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.5">
        <question>
          <para>Entity Attributes: &lt;bounds&gt; minimum and maximum are of type
          xs:float</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1, &lt;bounds&gt; elements elements were typed as 
          xs:decimal and did not support scientific notation. The base data type 
          was changed to 'xs:float' to accommodate both decimal and scientific 
          notation while maintaining backward compatibility. Authors should keep 
          in mind that there are still advantages to using decimal numbers for bounds, 
          because the decimal data type maintains precision during storage while 
          the floating point type does not. An alternative datatype, "precisionDecimal" 
          (corresponding to the IEEE type "floating-point decimal”), may be available 
          in the next version of XML Schema (i.e. v1.1, a working draft as of late 2008).
           It combines features of both the decimal and float types in that it supports 
           the same values and notation of a float, but is treated as decimal in arithmetic 
           and storage. The typing of this element may be changed to this new 
           type in a future release of EML. </para>
          <para>In EML 2.1.0, bounds can be written as: <programlisting><![CDATA[
<attribute>
 ...
 <numericDomain>
  <numberType>real</numberType>
  <bounds>
   <minimum>0</minimum>
   <maximum>1.234E15</maximum>
 </bounds>
</numericDomain>
</attribute>
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.6">
        <question>
          <para>Geographic Coverage: &lt;altitudeUnits&gt; use Standard Units of
          LengthType</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.0 and 2.0.1, altitude units were typed as xs:string, 
          and EML authors were instructed to include a vertical datum along 
          with the unit. In EML 2.1.0 this has been revised. Altitudes are now 
          restricted to lengths in Standard Units (e.g. meter, foot, etc), and the 
          datum must be placed in the geographicDescription element. Document 
          authors should note that including any additional content in the  
          &lt;altitudeUnits&gt; element other than a length value, such as the datum, 
          is not valid in EML 2.1.0.<programlisting><![CDATA[
..
<boundingCoordinates>
 ...
 <boundingAltitudes>
  <altitudeMinimum>0</altitudeMinimum>
  <altitudeMaximum>120</altitudeMaximum>
  <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
 </boundingAltitudes>
</boundingCoordinates>
..
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.7">
        <question>
          <para>Geographic Coverage: Latitude and Longitude are type xs:decimal, with appropriate
            ranges</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1, latitude and longitude values in &lt;geographicCoverage&gt;
           elements were typed as a xs:string. In EML 2.1.0 these values are restricted to 
           decimal numbers with realistic ranges (-90 to 90, and -180 to 180, respectively). 
           Fractions of a degree in minutes and seconds should be converted to decimal 
           format, and strings denoting direction or hemisphere (e.g., 'S' or 'south') are not 
           allowed. South latitudes and west longitudes must be indicated by a minus 
           sign (-) in front of the coordinate, as in the example below. These constraints 
           are consistent with the intended use of this field, which is to support mapping 
           the general geographic coverage of EML resources. Authors should keep in 
           mind that very specific descriptions of spatial data can be accommodated by 
           EML modules dedicated to that purpose. <programlisting><![CDATA[
..
<boundingCoordinates>
 <westBoundingCoordinate>-120.2534</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-119.7550</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>34.2231</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>34.1231</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
..
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.8">
        <question>
          <para>Element content must be non-empty</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1, elements of the string data type were allowed to be 
          empty or contain only whitespace, even for required elements. This feature 
          was occasionally exploited as a work-around to force incomplete documents 
          to validate in XML editors and the Metacat harvester, but this practice can 
          potentially cause problems parsing and using EML in tools such as Kepler. 
          In EML 2.1.0, string-content is now typed as "NonEmptyString" and string 
          entities are required to have minimal string content. So, whereas the following 
          content would have been allowed in EML 2.0.1: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
  <mediumName> </mediumName>
...
]]>
or 
<![CDATA[
...
  <attributeName/>
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
          <para>In EML 2.1.0, empty (or whitespace) content is not allowed. Actual content must be
            provided. <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
  <attributeName>approx. temperature</attributeName>
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.9">
        <question>
          <para>An offline resource has a minimum of one element required
            (&lt;mediumName&gt;) </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1, an author could describe an offline data resource, but include no
            information about the resource's distribution. In EML-2.1.0, minimal content (one
            element) is now required. </para>
          <para> In EML 2.0.1, the distribution tree for an offline resource could have ended with
            no content: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
<distribution>
 <offline/>
</distribution>
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
          <para> In EML 2.1.0, the element &lt;mediumName&gt; is required: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
<distribution>
 <offline>
  <mediumName>Atlas of Lake Erie Shorelines</mediumName>
 </offline>
</distribution>
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.10">
        <question>
          <para>Methods elements are standardized to &lt;methods&gt;</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1, both "&lt;method&gt;" and "&lt;methods&gt;" elements were included 
          in te schema, which caused confusion for some authors. In EML
            2.1.0, instances of the MethodsType have been standardized to 
            "methods". </para>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1, this path existed: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
/eml/dataset/dataTable/attribute/method/
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
          <para>In EML 2.1.0, this path is now properly constructed as: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
/eml/dataset/dataTable/attribute/methods/
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.11">
        <question>
          <para>Elements for date-time have been standardized to &lt;dateTime&gt;</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1,  both "&lt;datetime&gt;" and
            "&lt;dateTime&gt;" elements were included, which caused confusion for some authors. In EML
            2.1.0, these instances have been standardized to "dateTime". </para>
          <para>In EML 2.0.1, this path existed: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
/eml/dataset/dataTable/attribute/measurementScale/datetime/
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
          <para>In EML 2.1.0, this path is now properly constructed as: <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
/eml/dataset/dataTable/attribute/measurementScale/dateTime/
...
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.12">
        <question>
          <para>For journal articles, the elements &lt;volume&gt; and
            &lt;pageRange&gt; are now optional</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Two elements describing journal articles in the literature schema (eml-literature.xsd),
           &lt;volume&gt; and &lt;pageRange&gt;, are now optional to permit
            articles-in-press to be described in EML.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.13">
        <question>
          <para>A Citation may have an optional &lt;contact&gt; tree</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Also, an optional &lt;contact&gt; tree has been added  in eml-literature.xsd
            to permit a contact to be designated for a publication. For example, a contact 
could be provided for reprint requests
            <programlisting/>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry id="id.14">
        <question>
          <para>New optional element (&lt;onlineDescription&gt;) for a description of an
            online resource</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>A new element, &lt;onlineDescription&gt;, was added to support providing 
          a brief description of
            the content of an online element's child. This optional element is available for both
            resource-level and physical-level distribution nodes, and is typed as a
            NonEmptyString. One possible use for the description is to provide optional content for
            the HTML anchor element that accompanies a URL. <programlisting/>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </section>
  <!--



converting your eml -->
  <section>
    <title>Converting EML documents from v2.0.0/1 to v2.1.0</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>About the EML conversion stylesheet</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>An XSL stylesheet, 'eml201to210.xsl' is provided with the EML 2.1.0
          distribution to convert valid EML 2.0-series documents to EML 2.1.0 
          (see the 'style' directory). The intent of this reference to not to provide comprehensive
            instructions for transforming XML documents since adequate information is available
            elsewhere. A few specific
            examples will be given here, along with recommended practices and discussion of issues
            likely to occur when transforming EML 2.0 to v2.1.  The reader is referred to XSLT references available at W3C schools (http://www.w3schools.com/xsl/), Wikipedia (http://www.wikipedia.org/), W3C (http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/) and various books for more information about using XSLT to transform XML documents.</para>
          <para>The stylesheet performs these basic tasks: <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Updates namespaces to eml-2.1.0 and stmml-1.1</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Encloses XML markup within &lt;additionalMetadata&gt; sections in
                  &lt;metadata&gt; tags</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Renames elements &lt;method&gt; and &lt;datetime&gt;</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Moves access trees:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>if an access tree was a child of a dataset, citation, software or
                      protocol, it will be moved to the eml-level.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>if an access tree is found in an additionalMetadata section which
                     references
                      a distribution node via a &lt;describes&gt; element, it will be
                      moved to the corresponding distribution node.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Replaces the content of the "packageId" attribute (see
                the root element, &lt;eml:eml&gt;) when a parameter named "package-id"
                is passed to it. Without the parameter, the existing packageId content is retained.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Converting EML instances using the XSL stylesheet</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>You will first need to identify or obtain a program (or programming language module) capable of transforming XML using an XSL stylesheet. Suitable programs are available for all computer platforms, and modules are included in or available for most programming and scripting languages. For example, Linux distributions generally include a command line utility called 'xsltproc', which is described below.
            <!-- There is also a utility written in Java from the
            ecoinformatics project: <ulink url="http://knb.ecoinformatics.org"
            >http://knb.ecoinformatics.org</ulink>. -->
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Here are examples illustrating how to transform an EML document from the
                 command line using xsltproc. In the first example, the redirect operator is used to save
                 the output to a file.     An explicit output argument can also be used instead of a redirect, e.g.:
       xsltproc -output eml210_doc.xml eml201to210.xsl eml201_doc.xml
                  <programlisting>
 xsltproc eml201to210.xsl eml201_doc.xml > eml210_doc.xml
                  </programlisting>
                To include a new value for the packageId attribute, the stylesheet will accept a parameter 
                 called 'package-id' from the calling program:
                  <programlisting>
 xsltproc -stringparam package-id knb-lter-sbc.1006.4 eml201to210.xsl eml201_doc.xml > eml210_doc.xml 
                  </programlisting>
                       More complete documentation for the xsltproc program is available at http://xmlsoft.org/XSLT/xsltproc2.html.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para> Methods in the Apache Xalan Java library (<ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/commandline.html">http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/commandline.html</ulink>) can also be used to run the transform from a Linux, Macintosh or Windows command line if a Java JRE (Java runtime environment) and the Xalan classes are installed. Use the ‘-IN’ parameter to specify the source document, ‘-XSL’ parameter to specify the stylesheet, and ‘-OUT’ parameter to specify the output filename, as follows:
                    <programlisting>
java org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process -IN eml201_doc.xml -XSL eml201to210.xsl -OUT eml210_doc.xml 
               </programlisting>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Windows users can also use Microsoft MSXML and the msxsl.exe command line utility, 
                  which is freely available
                  from sources such as  <ulink url="http://www.download.com/windows/">CNET</ulink> and included with SynchroSoft’s oXygen XML editor.
                    <programlisting>
msxsl eml201_doc.xml eml201to210.xsl -o eml210_doc.xml                </programlisting>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Validity of new EML 2.1.0 documents</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Document authors are advised to check the validity of their new EML 2.1 using the
            EML parser after transformation for two reasons. First, additionalMetadata sections are
            parsed laxly, and so it is possible for additionalMetadata content in EML-2.0.0/1 to
            contain markup (i.e., access trees) that when moved, would result in invalid EML 2.1.0.
            Secondly, in EML 2.1.0, the content of several elements has been more tightly
            constrained (e.g., latitude and longitude), and so some content that was valid in EML
            2.0.1 will not be valid EML 2.1.0. EML instance documents can be validated in two ways: <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>With the <ulink url="http://knb.ecoinformatics.org/emlparser/ ">online EML
                    Parser. </ulink>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Using the Parser that comes with EML. To execute it, change into the 'lib'
                  directory of the EML release and run the 'runEMLParser' script passing your EML
                  instance file as a parameter. </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </para>
          <para>
           There are 3 cases in which the stylesheeet issues a warning or stops a transformation.  
          <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>An access tree is present in additonalMetadata, but could not be moved because an adjacent describes element did not reference a distribution node: The stylesheet prints a warning message and the transformation continues without moving the access tree.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Empty content in an element now typed nonEmptyString: transformation is stopped, and a message printed with the path to the invalid content. </para>
              </listitem>
                           <listitem>
                <para>something elset. </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Notes regarding EML and Metacat</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>If you are planning to contribute your EML 2.1.0  document in Metacat, note 
                  that the Metacat servlet checks incoming documents for validity as part of the insertion process.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Metacat submitters should be aware that some EML instances have content in the
                  'packageId' attribute which is intended to match Metacat's docid. In this case, it is 
                  recommended that you make use of the stylesheet's 'package-id' parameter to increment
                  the revision number.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
    <para>&nbsp;</para>
  </section>
</article>
